hello everyone welcome
to the active inference Institute
quarterly Roundtable number two in 2023.
it's June 30th 2023 and this is going to
be our quarterly updates and ways that
you can participate at The Institute and
in the active ecosystem
so welcome to the octave inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
you can find us at the links on this
page and note that we'll be
transitioning our emails over from
activeinference gmail.com towards
activeinference.institute domains
this is recorded in an archive live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
today in the quarterly meeting number
two of the year we'll start at The
Institute scale give some updates at The
Institute level and then we'll look a
little bit deeper into primarily
education but also research and then
I'll have some closing Thoughts by way
of a presidential address about where
we're at with active inference and if
you're watching live please write
comments and questions in the live chat
and we will look to address those during
okay so starting with the uh Institute
scale some updates coming from The
Institute
here's one way that we can visualize
the octave inference Institute in June
we are within the active inference
ecosystem as well as within other
ecosystems
and we have a nested structure Alex
would you like to describe this
oh yeah I think for these moments it's
great to see this structure and
understand what that is actually in
place and working and acting and
adapting
and from very beginning we considered
From perspective of systems thinking and
From perspective of act different
currents we always think about some kind
of Mass state and hierarchical structure
which can be builded and structured
accordingly
so having it right now
like embodied
it's great to see it
totally agree at The Institute scale
where these first updates are going to
come from we have the officers the board
of directors and the scientific Advisory
Board
we have two organizational units which
Steward the development and support
participation in projects and projects
and learning groups are really where it
happens on the ground and so we're going
to talk a lot more about these but this
is the nesting and our own relationship
with the ecosystem
another way to to see this is in terms
of people and positions at The Institute
so starting from the left we have casual
engagement with our products and
services into the niche so this might be
the very video that you're listening to
or watching right now it could be the
transcript of this video that you're
reading it might be the active inference
ontology it might be the active block
for a software package there's all these
different open source products and
services that we provide to the niche
and one moment you will decide to
participate in a project or a learning
group and that can be more towards
learning more towards the doing and
leveraging your contributions at The
Institute and some participants will
choose to solidify their participation
through volunteering or engaging with
the internship program both of which are
new and really excitingly developing
well
and then
we haven't listed any names of the the
many of you who are in all of these
different stages
and you may want to
play another role or another position in
the Institute such as the scientific
Advisory board board of directors or the
officers so
a lot of appreciation and thanks to
everybody who's shown and not shown on
this slide
um we are really appreciative of how you
all show up for the Institute
Alex want to add anything on that
um yeah even from this slide we can say
that a lot of people are already
involved in activity and provide great
insights and different perspective and
backgrounds and experience
and yes a lot of people not showing here
but we know when through our community
platforms and so on
so you can see this progress in terms of
participation in activities and it's
also great progress
all right moving on we are excited that
for our third applied active inference
Symposium to be held in August we will
have the theme of enacting ecosystems of
shared intelligence active inference as
a cognitive kernel we have a really
Broad and Global co-organizer team which
is very exciting so thanks to everybody
who's in the co-organizing team for this
Symposium we're just getting started on
the organization so in the coming days
and weeks we'll be providing more
information on participating in a more
formal call for presenters
however if you're listening to this
message now and you are really excited
to do a presentation or a workshop or
mentorship and be a part of the active
inference ecosystem then please reach
out to us
Alex anything you want to add here
but actually yes I think
we can remember but it will be a third
symposium
and it's cool but we have but here
earlier written
for this type of activity and hopefully
this event
bring us and for people who will
participate
you know insights connections and
ground for future developments in the
research
all right just uh
summarize and update a few of the
Institute level programs so volunteering
at the Institute
it's a way to engage it is just making
it that much easier to get involved with
one or more projects and to start to get
that recognition from The Institute
understanding your contributions and
also on your own resume your own work
history your portfolio
volunteering is really an incredible way
to learn by doing if you want to apply
or learn about organizational active
inference or if you want to think about
communication as active inference
education in the context of active
inference gripper and the gripped if you
want a perspective Swap and see it
multiple ways learning by doing on a
project through volunteering we hope is
a really unique opportunity and what you
do will and does really matter so if
you're taking notes on the margin of
some paper or if you're developing lists
that you felt like help your onboarding
into active inference you can make a
leveraged contribution by sharing that
kind of information or if you're not
quite sure what type of contribution or
the impact you would have we can help
find that kind of a niche for you
the internship program is
being a volunteer but wanting a little
bit more structure around that we have
about 20 currently active interns from
all around the world different
backgrounds levels of technical
familiarity with the active inference
ranging from truly some of the people
who I believe are experts to people who
just found out about active inference
and wanted to use this program to
accelerate their learning a lot
also in the last weeks and months I
would like to commend the two
individuals who know who they are who
have completed their internship this has
really been a great honor to work with
you both of you and to those who are
still active I look forward to seeing
those updates and continuing to work
with you the internship consists of
learning doing and also mentorship and
facilitation so interns tend to
participate in one or more course or
textbook group or maybe help out with
some live streams
interns engage on projects and that is
usually
a minimum of two projects one is hosted
at The Institute so some of the projects
that we'll look at later in this round
table but then also most of the interns
have a personal or background research
agenda so sometimes they make very small
contributions to an Institute project
but they're working really diligently on
their dissertation or on their hobby
project other times it's most of the
contribution to the Institute project
and then a little bit of self-guided
research and we try to provide our
interns with Support over multiple
spatial and temporal scales
foreign
engagement in the broader digital cyber
physical Niche we continue to grow on
our different platforms and channels
though these are just proxy measures in
our Discord podcast Twitter and YouTube
as well as mailing lists so we continue
to communicate out to those who want to
hear
here's a big picture on Institute
activities and you can find this
information at the activities page
that's uh listed here
at the top we have type of project
publication
live streams such as the one happening
right now and the active inference
Journal which picks up when the live
stream hits stop and transcribes and
curates publishes that transcript which
we'll talk more about
so live streams in journal are a great
pair
in the active block prints project we
continue to build the soft and hard
skills
associated with generative modeling in
the active inference tradition and so we
use the complex adaptive systems
modeling framework cadcad to implement
different active inference generative
models this is a really great place a
lot of discussions about modeling
Robotics and embodied JF claudger
continues to offer his expertise and
updates from this really incredible
project where real Lego robots are
implementing symbolic active inference
so thanks Jeff for
hosting this project the way you do
in the active inference ontology we
continue to refine and update the octave
inference ontology which is the real
language that we speak whether it
happens to be deployed in English or
visually or in a programming language or
however the active inference ontology is
how we're communicating and we develop
that and offer it as a service to the
niche in this project
we have multiple ongoing learning groups
which we'll talk more about soon but we
have a textbook group with par at all
the 2022 active inference textbook we
have sanjiv namjoshi who's writing a
really incredible work that will be a
textbook published as fundamentals of
active inference and we're Alpha Testing
along with Sanjeev and right there
alongside him so thanks Sanji for
bringing this work in progress to The
Institute and to to really sticking with
the trouble
this is going to be an incredible
product
and we have two courses one on physics
as information processing and one on
active inference for the social sciences
which we'll address soon and also
multiple times per week in our Discord
we have open discussions for Education
and Research so if this is all a lot or
you're not sure about anything probably
the best way to just drop in and find
out would be to check out when and how
we're meeting and come to the open
discussions if you just want to like
see what's up anything you want to add
there Alex
yeah
good to see that projects are active and
the mostly maybe for last period of time
it's uh having that new courses which
will describe later but
heaven and feeling me it's growing
it's provide great
opportunities for second half of the
year
so true
in the first quarterly Round Table we
had no courses but as of now we can say
that there are two courses that are
really pushing the frontier of education
and even research in Quantum information
sciences and in social sciences so
thanks again we'll get to those soon
all right let's dive into a little more
detail on eduactive so
Alex would you like to first introduce
and give a little thoughts on the active
inference qualification system draft
yeah we put it here like for now it's
education iterative scale but future
it's uh will be
applied for all
Institute structure and activities we
should have some Cornerstone in terms of
how we can measure
effectiveness of our educational
activities and Educational Services
in the beginning to understand courses
and our materials how
we change actually someone's mind and
how deep this might need to be changed
in some formal sense
and we take we not started from
Greenfield we just take one of a stable
system of qualifications level
from European
and adapted for how we can see it in
application to active inference and
participations and projects and so on
and for now we have a basic draft and
we'll have discussions around these
interested parties and different skills
of Institute and finally have some
some stable form location will apply to
a different direction
thanks
I'll just add a few notes on this first
just echoing your last point if you're
interested in active inference
professionalization education
qualification systems even as a Critic
we would really love to have you in the
game so please participate early
participate often and I'll just
highlight a few pieces of this system
draft
that are really exciting
first it begins at level zero which
everybody de facto can have perhaps even
upon or before birth
then as the levels proceed
active inference is always being
connected with domains and systems of
Interest so it's about yes and with
active inference about connecting active
inference to other fields and topics
understanding a different domain's
ontology robotics or Neuroscience or
pure mathematics whatever it may be
and working with active inference as you
gain knowledge of the ontology and of
the details of active inference but it's
not just a knowledge-based qualification
system
we also are looking to integrate skills
and even project responsibility and
autonomy so just to give kind of an
example of this
levels one and two again currently very
tentative drafts so for your engagement
but in levels one and two
people are able to act as basic Learners
and collaborators
and begin to get a grasp on what terms
we're using in active inference and how
do those Concepts relate to their field
of interest and we see this every single
day in the textbook group and in
discussions someone says oh I'm working
as a physical therapist and so in action
that's like the person moving their arm
that is where these levels are targeted
level three begins to get into
describing and understanding some of the
technical details of what we do
level four begins to approach the
evaluation and recapitulation
of technical models in active inference
level five is related to comprehensive
development and implementation as well
as in the projects and autonomy
exerting more supervision for self and
others
level six developing Advanced skills
level seven engaging with very
specialized problem-solving skills
and level eight engaging in synthesis
evaluation and critical problem solving
so
again can't emphasize enough it's just a
draft and we are calling for your
participation if this is something that
you would be interested in using or
engaging with but we think this is going
to be a really important direction for
the active inference ecosystem
carry on
to the textbook group
so in the active inference textbook
group
we are working on and through the par
pazulo and friston 2022 textbook
currently we have cohort three
working on the second half of the book
and cohort four on the first half of the
book
together these two cohorts compromise
about 150 people
not every person joins every meeting
some people engage with the recordings
asynchronously other people are in our
shared epistemic niche just gleaning and
contributing
to this kind of collaborative
stigmergic process
as educators
were focused on the continual delivery
and deployment of questions and
enrichment and discourse and just some
ways that this plays out here are for
example questions that people have asked
live or before or after a synchronous
meeting where we can connect the
specific figures and the ontology terms
to people's uncertainties
and
on the right
is an example of an equation here's the
variational free energy equation 2.5 and
the way that we can use the ontology to
unpack and connect some of the dots with
these equations and in the last few
weeks
we've actually taken that even further
and explored how to use language models
through code AI in this process so here
we have equations 2.1 and equations 2.2
they are being rendered in coda
via typing in latex
and then we are using language models
within Coda to provide explanations
contextualizations for different
backgrounds and expertises and also
translation into different languages
describing the variables and the
notation and the who what and why so
this has been a pretty fun Avenue and a
really cool example of how language
models and education can be hand in hand
and Empower our own learning by using
all kinds of models to help us where
frankly it can be quite challenging
which is in understanding some of the
analytical details of the framework
anything you want to add Alex
this is that type of technology which
looks like magic
and but and then but
heaven in place ontology
which is nicely integrated for Coda
again to all projects it's really
like imagine
for this car
which which is getting more and more big
cool
okay
in May 2023 we began our first course at
The Institute and that was physics as
information processing being taught by
one of the leading researchers in the
area Chris fields
and with a math PhD course assistant
Andre Aguirre so Chris thank you for
stepping up again from a scientific
Advisory Board to offer this truly
incredible and unique educational
experience
we've had
massive response
dozens of registrants who want to engage
in the participatory discussions that
happen in between your lectures
the second discussion being tomorrow for
those who want to join and 1500 views of
the first lecture in a month there's
many people who are following along the
course syllabus is explicit and
innovative
we have a question and answer system so
that people can ask questions
asynchronously Chris then answers them
and we have them posted again through
this interactive Coda interface and
that's really supporting an incredible
level of discourse and participation all
transcripts are going to be curated and
published along with the questions and
answers and some other supplemental
information
so this has been a really great
experience and something new over the
last few months
anything you want to add I'm tempted to
just talk about how cool the
Quantum information free energy
principle is but but perhaps now is not
the moment
um for me it's uh
uh like historically for my all the
ground stop change from beginning on
this uh Century starting from I.T
technology
technologist and computer science and
this notion of information processing
it always was like in Engineering in
engineering stands like a work in field
and working domain
and but I always had that need and
feeling for first principles for physics
in place
and for now seeing with that latest
developments on Quantum Quantum
information Theory and how it's nicely
connects to free energy and active
inference it's really really great to
have this Frontier curves
uh in place in our activities and
really really great thanks to police and
Hunter
and I believe that it's a kind of
starting point
maybe 10 years after we'll come back all
together and discuss how this course
started so great changes for different
ecosystems
thank you Alex totally agree
and also
we are fresh off the presses happy to
announce the second course that we'll be
offering at The Institute which is
constructing cultural landscapes active
inference for the social sciences and
this is going to be a
multi-teacher massively participatory
course
Avail of Kairos research thank you for
taking the initiative to suggest even
this possibility
and Ben and Mal Lorena thanks a lot for
joining on for the journey
on July 7th we will begin and it will
have some lecture sessions as well as
participatory discussion sections all
sessions sessions
are free
they'll be live streamed and rewatchable
the transcripts will be curated and
published into a book at the end of the
year and this is going to be a really
great on-ramp and space for people with
the humanities or social sciences
background so we've heard
people waiting for such a thing it was
aval's Insight that such a course could
be hosted
at Kairos research and at the Active
inference Institute so
thanks to all the teachers here and just
really looking forward to how you tackle
and engage with this question of active
inference in the social sciences
anything you want to add
uh yeah like this two different courses
like from
different to distant scales like from
Quantum scale and social scale and
possibly it's like two different ends of
spectrum in which we can work on with
our research and education
but it's great that this step to social
sciences because it brings active
influence and it's formal and first
place principled framework
into the domain which
haven't got it before and
now it's a great beginning also and our
scales between Quantum and social
will be on us to work on next years
yes and uh the kind of Aura Boris or
horseshoe Theory with Quantum social
sciences
onto the live streams so a lot to say of
course a little bit meta since we're on
a live stream right now but I'll just
note a few things
um first across our different series
we now have
336 completed or planned live streams so
most of those have already happened but
there are several that are planned but
we're over 300 completed and 336 as of
now being planned
and even just specifically looking at
the next 30 days we have just such a
breadth and depth
it's quite exciting to to watch let
alone to enact we'll have the Chris
Fields course
a discussion section a lecture and then
another discussion section we'll begin
the active inference for the social
sciences course with avell Ben having
contributions
we'll have a guest stream with
professors from around the world
researchers all these different topics
being able to be slotted in with a
really great way to platform and give
visibility and catalyze discussion
around these incredible researchers
work so it's really exciting and it
would be great not going to say it's
specifically a personal request but if
you choose to read it as such then great
it would be awesome to have more
assistance with participating and
preparing and enacting live streams we
have a role-based ways of planning and
preparing and enacting live streams so
whether you want to play a more
technical or operational or logistical
role if you want to be a conversational
facilitator if you want to do it in a
different language if you want to do a
series there's so many ways that you can
get involved but it would just be
awesome to have more voices on the live
stream and just be able to continue
offering these kinds of resources at
even faster rate with increased
professionalization and I know that
there's many people out there who
would be incredible contributors to
broadcast and or facilitate
everyone is also welcome to
self-nominate or suggest or introduce
somebody who you think would fit well on
a stream if it's like a perspective that
we haven't heard from that would be
really important
there's a lot of background Technical
and educational work on the dot zero
videos when we do a paper discussion so
if there's a paper that you want to have
a a million x leveraged contribution on
your preparation around
if we discuss that in a live stream and
you're able to help before with the dot
zero you'll be a co-author on a research
publication of the transcript
and you'll have made an absolutely
unique Irreplaceable contribution to
active inference knowledge
with what you did in your diligence in
the dot zero so for people who hear that
calling that's incredibly important
we invite people to share the live
streams on social media or with their
colleagues however they find it relevant
like if there's a topic or a person that
has come up on our streams sharing it
where relevant will help bring people in
and also we have weekly live stream
meetings so if you just want to find out
like what we do and how we do it in the
live streams then I would recommend that
you join the regular meetings and if you
really want to join but that time never
works for you then email and let us know
that you're specifically interested
we'll find a different time
any other comments there Alex
oh this moments we can see that
oh
but a lot of live stream activity is
happening this participation of people
not only with our own preparations about
these people who just want to share this
and so on
and if we can keep this Rhythm to having
different people with their interests
and sharing ideas
and yes if people will join to help us
to do it more and more often Maybe
it will be great
thank you
the active inference Journal picks up
where live stream stops
the active inference Journal is engaged
in continuous deployment and development
of speech to text transcription
automated and manual editing curation
and finally publication so just to give
an example a live stream will occur and
then we use speech to text onto a public
GitHub repository everybody can edit the
markdown file and then we're able to
publish those transcripts so that they
can be citable so that a conversation
someone has can go onto their resume as
a true citable publication
and we can just facilitate the
accessibility and the findability of
these incredible
conversations and moments that we have
and also in the active inference Journal
we're always developing the process from
setup for those of all technical
backgrounds how to get things working on
your own local setup or on a cloud setup
using free and open source software
where possible
the speech to text
the text processing
the editing translating into languages
rendering into a diversity of formats
publishing through different channels
and then engaging in further analysis
related to natural language processing
and the active inference ontology all
these fun things we can do so if you
in an alternate Multiverse we're a
librarian or an editor or a viewer or an
advocate of the active inference Corpus
bring it into this reality and make a
huge contribution
by cultivating our epistemic garden and
our offerings because there's so much
enrichment that can happen with past
streams and with proactively letting the
live stream project know and letting
courses know
how we can help them at the journal to
develop these kinds of Publications that
in new ways are expanding definitions of
scholarship and research and service
anything else to add
yeah
as for this project I I believe it's
like most technical
in The Institute and maybe we can call
it more probably like language
processing project
and maybe it is a good starting point
for people who got who have good
technical skills some programming skills
which are related to language processing
in general or some specific part of it
and maybe it will be of interest for
them to start from this project and
later I get a better grasp on what is
active influence is
awesome totally agree it's like
seeing the range of live streams is
really one of the best ways to just jump
into understanding the the waste and the
topics that people speak
okay
we'll just briefly mention the research
work happening but this last several
month period has been extremely focused
and extremely productive on education we
have the two new courses the
qualification system all of these other
curricular developments
um so there's several ongoing research
projects we have the active inference
ontology as a research and development
initiative active block prints as a
software package for complex systems
modeling using active inference
Robotics and embodied with jf's symbolic
active inference robots and then there's
some project seeds that we always love
to offer up to interns or to volunteers
as something that they can like restart
and take a lot of initiative something
that's just planted but but barely there
and that right now is the graphical
interface with thinking really
expansively about what it looks like to
learn an apply active inference
from a embodied perspective
and cognitive agent modeling
doing meta-analysis and synthesis across
different cognitive modeling Frameworks
so that we can really have a place to
point when we describe how different
cognitive phenomena
speaking to a cognitive pattern language
are implemented or addressed by active
inference and other Frameworks
and then there's the so many of you who
engage in individual research so there's
a lot of research happening in the space
and we see education as a fundamental
enablement for research
as part of the institute's mission for
Education and Research development so
it's been good times with research and
uh
I'm really excited to see all the all
the projects that people share during
sessions start to develop and and
flourish
anything else you want to add about
research Alex
uh yeah maybe uh this direction was not
so active last times but as we discussed
for future directions that we will
bring more attention and to more efforts
to maybe
formalize a bit per week as Institute
service
people around from ecosystems uh how we
can support them on their ways
and so on so
it will be good times here too
yeah agreed we want to provide a lot of
research services so for people who who
want to be on any side of that table
Reach Out
all right
well the last section here
is going to be a short active inference
based presidential address
I will be just speaking to some recent
developments as well as past
developments in the active inference
space and just give a few thoughts on
how they relate to the active inference
Institute and what we're all doing here
if you're watching live please write
some questions or comments into the live
chat and at the end of this short
address
we will review any other comments or
questions from those who are here live
give some last thoughts and then we'll
be back into the work so I wanted to
begin this address with a reference to
the work that was before active
inference Institute which was active
inference lab but even before active
inference lab there was the
collaboration with Alex Yvonne Alexandra
RJ and myself around active inference
and behavior engineering for teams and
organizations
and this was in September 2020 only a
few years ago now
more than two but less than three years
ago
and uh it's amazing how far things have
come and at the same time how many of
the topics that we were able to bring
into this context of remote teams and
organizations
still ring as relevance
and they're just gestured to here
we've gone far towards enacting and
implementing and improving but still we
can think about cognitive entities
engaged in the Cyber physical niche
with narrative and rhetoric structuring
their understanding
of how sensory data translate into
action so for people who are interested
in this topic we invite you one way or
another to engage with us on this
journey
because we are only going to do it all
together so just wanted to begin with
that kind of callback to several years
ago though so much has changed certainly
for all of us in the times between that
when we really find first principles
approaches like active inference and
when we really care about systems of
interest and communities then
the actions that we take we don't regret
but I think we can go into a little bit
more detail and reference some recent
developments in the active inference
ecosystem that speak to how day after
day week after week our system of
Interest active inference learning and
application
really gifts or blesses us with new ways
of thinking and new ways of acting so
for example just within the last months
the inner screen model of Consciousness
was released as a preprint by Maxwell
ramstead at all
dealing with all these topics that we
know and love and building upon the
quantum free energy principle formalism
which again it's easy to forget was not
even in place two years ago discussed in
live stream number 40.
and weeks after publication we're able
to enact
a conversation hearing from voices all
over the world
bringing experts and those with
different backgrounds onto the screen
here the screen that you see is the
classical information
depository that enables us as Quantum
cognitive agents to engage with each
other and so all of these beautiful
people on the Stream
who with their regime of attention and
their Quantum cognitive rotation brought
to bear
their attention and their language
contribution through action
we are able to inscribe that on
classical digital artifacts like live
streams and transcripts and then provide
it to the niche for all of you to rotate
that into your own space and context so
again the spatial temporal and
conceptual linkages are happening at a
speed that is boggling
and on the right is a paper from just
this month officially by Thomas Parr at
all cognitive effort and active
inference and I have the image small
because there's more details to go into
in the paper
however
they used a well-known model of
cognitive burden called a Stroop model
which shows a color
written out as a word and that word is
shown in some color so the color red
written in red the color red written in
blue
and the timing dynamics of people's
reading behavior and recognition
behavior is a proxy for cognitive effort
and so
this is just one more not even Brick in
the Wall not even just one tool in the
tool kit but like another lens or layer
or ability or capacity for active
inference framework which adds these
features affect memory anticipation all
these different features are layered in
like a symphony without developing bloat
because the first principles kernel the
cognitive firmware is not getting
bloated
it is staying at first principles and
sometimes it feels like even diving down
to zero with principles
while Advanced research in the space is
able to help us understand
really sophisticated cognitive phenomena
like cognitive effort now one can look
back through the previous stream and
what we discussed and how could
cognitive effort help us support the
accessibility rigor and applicability of
active inference it's such a natural
question and again week after week our
Niche provides us with new ways of
thinking and doing so it's so fun to be
gripping and gripped within active
inference
I'd like to recognize and commend
Jacob's excellent work
just in April we published generalized
notation notation for active inference
models
GNN generalized notation notation is a
plain text format for conveying active
inference generative models it's
something like a dialect of markdown
and it brings us closer and closer to
the Triple Play The Triple Play is the
idea that we should have integrity
amongst multiple representations of
active inference models
that is
what we see visualized graphically or
tangibly
what we hear and say in terms of the
natural language use
and with executable cognitive
simulations
so if someone looks at an organizational
flowchart and there's three A's
connected to two B's
that is something that we can visualize
describe and execute so that there isn't
a front and a back room conversation
rather there's an integrated
conversation that allows for everybody
to make contributions in the modalities
and in the ways that they want and the
interlingua
not the only interlingua and by no means
its final version
is the plain text generalized notation
notation we're having a lot of fun
working with language models and
visualizing this transforming it into
executable simulations and so thanks
again jaka for the really creative and
dedicated work because this
method
is going to be a real core functionality
for translating across visual elements
our natural languages
and the kinds of simulations that we
want to run
and I'll close with a recent publication
with Carl friston at all including
myself and blue so two out of three
officers on the paper not terrible
and in this paper we used free energy
principle and active inference to
provide something like a measuring or an
observability framework for Ecology
Evolution and development or eco-evo
Devo and the way that this was done is
through the renormalization group of
physics and so in this image on the left
we can see it as like maybe a bunch of
cells which each contain organelles and
those cells make a tissue or the big
circle might be the population of
organisms or the ecosystem Community
again recognizing the nested niche
engagement within and across levels of
spatial and temporal modeling
and
looking at just two layers and how
they're connected
we can think of that as a nested action
perception cycle
so here's like the behavior sensory
um and the behavior of of a worm in this
case
happening at whatever time scale it's
being modeled at and then at the slower
or the deeper level of the hierarchical
model
we have the Bayesian learning like
process of the extended genotype
happening in a slower adaptive layer and
so this should
clearly
connect
to what we said at the very beginning of
the stream about the Institute as part
of a nested system
here we have the ecosystem
the space around
here's the Institute this is what it
really means to enter and to join not
just to look into
but to be on or in the Institute
and then the kinds of dynamic partitions
that were able to embody within the
Institute through our Communications and
and through our actions
and so
it's just so exciting to see
everyone's incredible research
contributions
the kinds of questions and developments
that even if I were not an author even
if I were not in the active inference
field I would believe are at least the
right things to be trying in terms of
bringing theoretical integration in
ecology Evolution and development at
least these are the right research
Avenues but then again to be able to act
infer and serve
through the Institute as a multi-scale
evolutionary entity in and of itself
this kind of real-time enactment of
multiple scales and Quantum reference
frames is something that is only arising
through co-creation so in closing I send
my deepest appreciation to all those who
support and care and engage
to those who are not sure
I welcome you
to the past the present and the future
we respect and that's why we do what we
do
so
Alex
where where do we go or what is next
thank you very much for the talk
and I'm really providing that so you
know
the reasons well from the beginning and
about going now
and congratulations on that
publication on evolutionary work and
it's a great opening Direction
and
the least
these direction will make a next step
into techno Revolution also
and we will use this Tech Revolution
customer approach
the develop Institute Canada consistent
yes I'll just wait a few more seconds if
anyone writes a
question that we can address in the live
chat
let's look at some of these questions
that we look at at the end of every live
stream
what would a good understanding enable
well if we were able to really
understand our own generative model as
The Institute and as the active
inference ecosystem it would support our
sense making and decision making we'd be
able to act and infer and serve better
what are the unique predictions and
implications
that's a very interesting question
I'm sure there are many ways to to
address this and we we did have many
future oriented Expressions during this
discussion even today
what are the next steps for free energy
principle and active inference
again do you have any thoughts on this
one the middle question or the second
question Alex
and the unique predictions and next
steps depends on some specific field or
domain or or all for ourselves we
understand whether to conferences scale
free approach
and it just
can be applied to any scale of research
or any domain which uh
researcher or engineer is working on
can be described to his active internal
language and stuff to informed from
where
using affordances to computational
modeling or some other types of modeling
and so on
yeah
yeah what are the goals of the research
to embody our mission to support the
active inference ecosystem to to be the
best Institute we can be be the best in
estimates within it what do you think
maybe we should remove goals okay here
let's change it to preferences
yeah at least
and considering
in open-endedness way again we're okay
we can speak about those ones it looks
like it's not so useful concept
yes sometimes when we're talking about
the um specific research papers we talk
about the goal of that paper but goal is
not to be found in the active inference
ontology
and
we find ways of making do and thriving
without needing to rest upon goals and
reward and that's really exciting and
that's something that a lot of people
don't even realize that they're steeped
in reward maximization and goal
implementation
until the open-endedness and the
Vitality of active inference
becomes understood
what are you still curious about
Ola you go first then I'll give the last
thought as we close
um I always remember our discussions
about sales of the world curios in the
beginning of
it's like
[Music]
I believe it
is
a week a week each day each month what
our appealth our Frontier are showing us
so much
a lot of different perspectives
different connections real people in
Communications and projects and so on so
it's happiness
very beautiful
I'm
curious about many things like that you
said that we uh develop and hone that
Curiosity every day and we we seek to to
spark and be sparked when people come in
from different backgrounds with their
Curiosities it's inspiring to say the
least and I'm really curious about who
will have listened or read this far in
the Stream
and choose that moment to take an action
to get involved with the Institute so
there's only one way that my uncertainty
is going to be reduced about that and I
think if you know you know so thank you
Alex thank you blue
thank you to the officers and to all of
the Institute
see you around
thank you thank you